Guide to the Gustavus Vasa Fox Collection 1823-1919 (bulk 1860-1889) MS 439.17
New-York Historical Society
- Series V. Memorabilia, souvenirs, and visual materials (1823-1890)
  - Satirical account of cut-off engines aboard Richmond U.S.S. and Pensacola: "The experiences of a poor devil with the concatenations of curtailing cut off or Uncle Sam paying dearly for his steam whistle - how our money goes", [1860s] (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Drawings caricatures: David D. Porter, 1862, 1883 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Engraved signature copperplates, [1860s] (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, [1860s], 1872 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Drawings, cards, 1872, undated (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Menu: Levi Woodbury 70th birthday, 1890 May 22 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Pennant: 1st Louisiana Artillery, Undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Invitation cards for Farragut celebration, Undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
- Series VI. Printed materials and clippings (1850-1883)
  The series includes publications and other printed information as well as newspaper clippings on the Woodbury family, and on Fox's areas of interest and related to his writings. Some of the commercial printed materials appear to have been collected randomly. The scrapbook pages are leaves from other books onto which clippings have been glued. The document on "small Vessels in which I have been concerned" is anonymous but appears to be written by Robert Bennett Forbes, based on the ships listed. One document is in Chinese and may be the guest list for an event Fox attended.
  The materials are arranged chronologically. The bundled clippings were originally stored separately; some of the other subject-related clippings were originally in other series and have been gathered together here. Some of the clippings were grouped by subject and others by time period; their original arrangement has been retained.
  - Woodbury family: Isaac O. Barnes oration, Montgomery Blair obituary, petition of Levi Woodbury heirs, 1850, 1882, 1883 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Bonds: Florida Railroad Company, and others; Confederate currency, 1856-1863 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Congressional publications, 1861, 1884 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - "Specifications and Plans: U.S. Iron-plated steam batteries", 1862 April (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Information on Monitor, 1862-1868 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1862-1880 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1862-1880 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - "Sketch showing the position of the compass station in Delaware River…", 1864 (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Commercial printed materials, 1865, 1871, 1878, undated (Box 19, Folder 16)
  - Southwest Pacific Railroad: printed materials, 1866-1881 (Box 19, Folder 17)
  - Southwest Pacific Railroad: clippings, 1867-1868 (Box 19, Folder 18)
  - Atlantic and Pacific Railroad: printed materials, 1867-1876 (Box 19, Folder 19)
  - Atlantic and Pacific Railroad clippings, 1868-1871 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - "Remarks of John Amory Lowell at the semi-centennial anniversary of the incorporation of Lowell, March 1, 1876", 1876 March 1 (Box 19, Folder 21)
  - Stewart-Meissonier letters about paintings, 1876 (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - "Hon. Montgomery Blair's letter on the presidency", 1876 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Campaign materials: Tilden vs. Hayes, 1876 (Box 19, Folder 24)
  - Bundled clippings, 1878-1883 (Box 19, Folder 25)
  - Bundled clippings "Miscellaneous", 1879-1882 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Bundled clippings, 1879-1883 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Bundled clippings "Political", 1880-1881 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Clippings scrapbook pages, 1878, undated (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Bound clippings, 1880 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - "Census bulletin no. 302," "Forestry bulletin no. 23", 1880, 1883 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Columbus Landing: Background, reviews, 1881, 1882, undated (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - G.V. Fox letter: Orphanage of St. John's Parish, 1883 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - "Notes in regard to the voyages of small vessels in which I have been concerned [Robert Bennett Forbes?], Undated (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Printed page in Chinese, undated (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - Statistical statement relating to South West Pacific Rail Road - Its lands, conditions and prospects, 1864 October 14 (Box OS 1, Folder 6)
  - Plan for U.S. Steam battery, 1868 (Box OS 2, Folder 5)
- Series VII. Virginia L. Woodbury Fox papers (1850-1896)
  The series includes letters sent (both originals and drafts) and received by Virginia Woodbury Fox, with recipients including her husband and other family members, as well as officials of St. John's Church in Washington, DC. After her husband's death, she donated land on which the Church erected an orphanage, with a plaque commemorating Gustavus Vasa Fox. Notes in her hand indicate that she destroyed much of her correspondence to her husband. Among those letters saved, and specifically marked, is that of July 20, 1863, describing the Draft Riots in New York City. Other highlights include a note (c. 1862) from Mary Lincoln and a separated envelope from President Abraham Lincoln.
  Biographical Note
  Virginia Lafayette Woodbury (1821-1908) was the daughter of Levi and Elizabeth Clapp Woodbury. She married Gustavus Vasa Fox in 1855; they had no children. Her sister, Mary Elizabeth, married Montgomery Blair and their children included Montgomery Blair, who was the Foxes' heir.
  Some of Virginia Woodbury Fox's letters to her husband are filed with his letters received in Series I. Correspondence. Others are included here with her family's papers: she appears to have retrieved them from her husband's papers and specifically organized them here herself.
  - Letters sent: family, 1850-1861 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Letters sent: family, 1863-1865 (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Letters sent: Gustavus Vasa Fox, 1863-1864 (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Letters sent: family, 1870-1877, [1880s] (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Letters sent: St. John's Church orphanage, Washington DC, 1885-1889 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Letters sent, 1891-1897 (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Letters received, 1860-1875 (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Letters received, 1880-1888 (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Letters received: St. John's Church orphanage, Washington DC, [1880s] (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Letters received, 1891-1896 (Box 20, Folder 21)
- Series VIII. Woodbury and Fox family papers (1832-1879)
  The series includes correspondence and personal papers of members of the Woodbury and Fox family, including Virginia Woodbury Fox's father Levi and uncle Isaac O. Barnes. Levi Woodbury's letters received include those signed by Presidents Andrew Jackson (1835) and James Buchanan (1847) and by Senator Thomas Hart Benton (1851). The letters received are originals; the letters sent are letterpress copies, some of which are difficult to read. Most of the Barnes letters were in alphabetical order, which has been retained; the 1850-1851 letters were originally in the Levi Woodbury correspondence and have been moved here with their original order retained.
  Levi Woodbury (1789-1851) served as Secretary of the Navy (1831-1834), Secretary of the Treasury (1834-1841), United States senator (1841-1845), and Associate Justice of the U.S. Supreme Court (1845-1851). The bulk of his and other Woodbury family papers are now in the Library of Congress. Levi Woodbury's sister Hannah (b. 1800) was married to Isaac O. Barnes (b. 1798). Gustavus Vasa Fox served as executor of Barnes's will. The materials give no indication of William Bowes Bradford's relation to the Woodbury family; G.W.M. Guild appears to have been a nephew of Fox's.
  - Levi Woodbury: Letters sent, 1832-1845 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Levi Woodbury: Letters received, 1832-1851, undated (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - William Bowes Bradford: will, 1835 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Isaac O. Barnes: Diary and memoranda, 1838 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Isaac O. Barnes: Letters received, 1850, 1851 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Isaac O. Barnes: Letters received, A-W, 1849-1856 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Isaac O. Barnes: Estate-related correspondence, documents, 1863-1866 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - G.W. M. Guild: Navy application and recommendations, 1877-1879 (Box 21, Folder 8)
- Series IX. Archival and filing records (1862-1919)
  Some correspondence in Series I was originally folded and then bundled in stacks between wooden boards, probably for storage in pigeonholes within a desk or cabinet. On the boards was written the content and date range of the stacked documents. A few were retained with the collection and are included here. This series also includes Virginia Woodbury Fox's notes regarding decisions she made about her husband's papers.
  - Filing boards: Press copies of private letters, 1862 A-Z (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Filing boards: G.V. Fox Unofficial, 1862 L-W (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - Filing boards, 1863 A-Z (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Archives processing notes, 1902, 1919 (Box 21, Folder 12)
- Series X. Bound Volumes (1838-1919)
  The bound volumes include Fox's letters (many to his future wife's uncle and aunt, Isaac O. and Hannah Woodbury Barnes) and journals from cruises on various vessels, a scrapbook about him collected by Virginia Woodbury Fox, a scrapbook of clippings created by a Blair or Fox family member, household accounts and records of the Foxes' stock and property holdings, two letter books (one containing letter press and one carbon copies), a writing portfolio that was a gift from Levi Woodbury, a relief map of New Hampshire's White Mountains, and the edited editions of Fox's correspondence published by the Naval History Society.
  Virginia Woodbury Fox's notes in Volume 1 indicate that she erased or deleted various sections that she deemed to be "too personal." Her note in her scrapbook documents its importance to her and to any future biographer of her husband.
  - Letters, Cruise to China and Russia, 1838-1851 (Volume 1)
  - "Scrapbook of newspaper clippings concerning Gustavus Vasa Fox, collected by his wife, Virginia L.W. Fox", 1852-1903 (Volume 2)
  - "Household Account Book, Expenses in Lawrence/ Expenses in Lowell/ Expenses in Boston", 1855-1876 (Volume 3)
  - Property Book: Stocks and bonds held by Fox, and Virginia L. Woodbury before and after their marriage, 1855-1882 (Volume 4)
  - Diary, Russia, 1866 June - December (Volume 5)
  - Letter book, 1869-1878 (Volume 6)
  - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings, [1860s] (Volume 7)
  - Letter book, 1878-1879 (Volume 8)
  - Scrapbook of clippings: "Matrimony and its happy results; Chronique scandaleuse", [1870s] (Volume 9)
  - Relief Map of the White Mountains, New Hampshire, [1870s] (Volume 10)
  - Leather writing portfolio, Undated (Volume 11)
  - "Confidential correspondence of Gustavus V. Fox, Assistant Secretary of the Navy 1861-1865, edited by Robert Means Thompson and Richard Wainwright, Vol. I. New York: Naval History Society", 1918 (Volume 12)
  - "Confidential correspondence of Gustavus V. Fox, Assistant Secretary of the Navy 1861-1865, edited by Robert Means Thompson and Richard Wainwright, Vol. I. New York: Naval History Society", 1918 (Volume 13)
  - "Confidential correspondence of Gustavus V. Fox, Assistant Secretary of the Navy 1861-1865, edited by Robert Means Thompson and Richard Wainwright, Vol. II. New York: Naval History Society", 1919 (Volume 14)
  - "Confidential correspondence of Gustavus V. Fox, Assistant Secretary of the Navy 1861-1865, edited by Robert Means Thompson and Richard Wainwright, Vol. II. New York: Naval History Society", 1919 (Volume 15)